<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Undefined Value - 2003</title><link href="https://undefinedvalue.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://undefinedvalue.com/feeds/2003.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://undefinedvalue.com/</id><updated>2003-12-31T03:59:00-05:00</updated><subtitle>Kris Johnson's Blog</subtitle><entry><title>My Failed Contracting Career</title><link href="https://undefinedvalue.com/my-failed-contracting-career.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2003-12-31T03:59:00-05:00</published><updated>2003-12-31T03:59:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Kristopher Johnson</name></author><id>tag:undefinedvalue.com,2003-12-31:/my-failed-contracting-career.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;After my last permanent position, I took a few months off from work, and
then tried to start a career as an independent consultant/contractor.
After many years of hearing about the freedom enjoyed by consultants,
and the exhorbitant fees they charged, I wanted to get my piece of the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After my last permanent position, I took a few months off from work, and
then tried to start a career as an independent consultant/contractor.
After many years of hearing about the freedom enjoyed by consultants,
and the exhorbitant fees they charged, I wanted to get my piece of the
action. People encouraged me to give it a try, because I had many of the
traits associated with independents: desire for variety, lots of
knowledge, no trouble voicing my opinions, and no dependents who would
go hungry if I couldn't find work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My primary motivation was the desire to be independent. I wanted that
whole be-you-own-boss thing. I wanted to be able to work less than 40
hours a week when I felt like it. I wanted to be able to choose which
assignments to take. I wanted to be able to decide what new computer to
buy and which development tools to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, this was mid 2002, and as all you people more clued into
reality than me know, that was a bad time to try to start a contracting
career. Established contractors were having trouble finding work. Those
who were finding work had to charge fractions of what they used to
charge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest reason I failed as a contractor was that I didn't have the
business sense for it. I didn't know anything about marketing. I didn't
know what my market niche would be. I didn't have a lot of contacts in
the industry. I hoped I could just post my resumé on my web site, and
jobs would start rolling in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did get a few calls, but most of them were for things that I wasn't
really prepared to do. For example, my resume lists Oracle and OpenVMS.
I was contacted by someone who needed me to provide training for
employees who would be administering Oracle on an OpenVMS system. Ten
years ago, when Oracle on OpenVMS was what I was doing, I may have been
able to do it, but it had been so long that I didn't think I could do a
reasonable job, so I had to pass. There were several other similar
opportunities that I passed on as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In hindsight, I wonder if I should have taken a few of those jobs. I
wouldn't have known what I was doing, but it would have been work and it
could have led to something I knew better. I have never been comfortable
claiming to be able to do things that I don't really know I can do.
Other consultants don't have that problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did manage to land a contract with a former employer. They did pay me
well, but unfortunately only had a few hours of work per month for me to
do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually, I gave up on the idea of being completely independent, and
signed up with one of those organizations that hires people out as
contractors. I got a good gig with them, but for no more money than I
would have received as a permanent employee, and without security or
benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I gave up on contracting, and got a permanent job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Will I ever go independent or start my own business again? Maybe. I
think I do have a strong entrepreneurial streak, and a disdain for
working at the direction of others. But I'm not going to try it again
until I have a better idea about what products or services I will
provide, and who will pay for them.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2003"></category><category term="contracting"></category><category term="self-indulgence"></category></entry><entry><title>New is Good?</title><link href="https://undefinedvalue.com/new-is-good.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2003-12-31T03:59:00-05:00</published><updated>2003-12-31T03:59:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Kristopher Johnson</name></author><id>tag:undefinedvalue.com,2003-12-31:/new-is-good.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Python is the coolest language ever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've never written a real Python program. But after reading the language
spec and a few tutorials, and writing a few simple programs, I am
fascinated with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like many other programmers, I love to play with new things. Learning is
fun. New challenges …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Python is the coolest language ever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've never written a real Python program. But after reading the language
spec and a few tutorials, and writing a few simple programs, I am
fascinated with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like many other programmers, I love to play with new things. Learning is
fun. New challenges are fun. Unfortunately, we often confuse enthusiasm
with evaluation. If we &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to use something, it must be superior to
all that junk we don't want to use anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;C++ is a horrible language. (Only Perl is uglier.) But when I am writing
important code, I use C++ instead of the "new" languages. I hate it, but
I know it well. It's limitations infuriate me, but I never get
surprised. Other developers deride me for using MFC and the Visual C++
wizards, but I am more productive and less error-prone with those tools
I've used for years than I would be with the "better" tools that I don't
know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Am I missing out by using old bad tools instead of new cool tools?
Maybe, I don't know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The distinction between "new" and "old" is not necessarily
chronological. For the past few years, I have been writing Palm OS
programs using &lt;a href="http://www.quartus.net/products/forth/"&gt;Forth&lt;/a&gt;. Forth is
certainly not a new language, having been around for decades, but it was
new to me. I loved the way I could create programs with a relatively
small amount of code. It was interesting to do all my programming and
debugging on the handheld device, without benefit of a desktop-based
cross-compiler and debugger. I remember the experience fondly, but I
can't kid myself into thinking I was more productive with Forth than I
would have been with a C compiler.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I once felt differently. In college and in my early professional years,
I was constantly learning about new programming languages and other
development tools. I'm sure that the study of all those things made me a
better programmer. However, I also believe that concentrating on a
couple of languages for many years has made me a better programmer than
I would be if I flitted between languages constantly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, all development tools and technologies suck, and the new
ones don't make things that much better. The hard part of software
development is figuring out exactly what the program needs to do. The
level of effort required to do that is independent of the programming
language used. Being able to pick the right tool for the job is
important, but usually the right tool is the one I know how to use most
proficiently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Python is the coolest language ever. I'll continue to believe that until
I actualy have to use it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2003"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="rant"></category></entry><entry><title>Welcome to My Blog</title><link href="https://undefinedvalue.com/welcome-to-my-blog.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2003-12-31T03:59:00-05:00</published><updated>2003-12-31T03:59:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Kristopher Johnson</name></author><id>tag:undefinedvalue.com,2003-12-31:/welcome-to-my-blog.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My name is Kris Johnson. For eleven years, I have been a computer
programmer. For the first few years, I enjoyed it. Now, I've grown tired
of it, but I don't have any other marketable skills and I don't want to
move into management. So, I do what I can …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My name is Kris Johnson. For eleven years, I have been a computer
programmer. For the first few years, I enjoyed it. Now, I've grown tired
of it, but I don't have any other marketable skills and I don't want to
move into management. So, I do what I can to improve my programming
skills in the hope that I can work less hard. I also like to exchange
ideas with others about how to make the programmer's life easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing is a great outlet for me. It helps me focus my thinking, and
gives me a way to vent my frustrations. I also like to think that others
benefit from reading what I write (although I've seen no evidence of
that). For a while, I interacted with the community at the &lt;a href="http://c2.com/cgi/wiki"&gt;C2
wiki&lt;/a&gt; (a.k.a., "Ward's Wiki"). I learned quite a
bit there. But that community has changed, and I don't think my writings
will fit there anymore, so from now on I'll write here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To avoid trouble, I'm going to refrain from writing about my current
job. If I do write about my job, it will be disguised so much that
nobody will know. However, most if not all of what I write will be about
what I've learned about software development, and about what I still
hope to learn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I may also occasionally post an "off-topic" item such as a movie or book
review, or just some odd thought I had while eating breakfast. But don't
worry; I don't have that many thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="2003"></category><category term="blog"></category><category term="self-indulgence"></category></entry></feed>